A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Education and Public Policy Program (EPP), Office of Mariam K. Chamberlain FA536
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Education and Public Policy Program (EPP), Office of Mariam K. Chamberlain
1963-1979
Rockefeller Archive Center
Chamberlain, Mariam
Ford Foundation
FA536
3.93 Cubic Feet 3 standard record storage boxes.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Arrangement
As received.
Scope and Contents
Primarily documents Chamberlain's work with the Coordinating Committee on Women's Programs and Task Force on Equal Opportunity and Treatment for Women.
Biographical / Historical
Mariam Kenosian Chamberlain (1918-2013) was a feminist activist and foundation executive whose work helped establish women's studies programs and women's research centers. Chamberlain worked as a Program Officer for many years at the Ford Foundation.
Chamberlain first worked at the Ford Foundation as a Program Assistant in its Economic Development and Administration Program. After leaving the Foundation in 1961, she returned to it in 1966 as a Program Officer in its Division of Education and Research, Higher Education and Research Program. She continued working in the Foundation's education related programs until she left the Foundation again in 1981. From 1974 to 1975, she served as the Chairperson for the Co-ordinating Committee for Women's Programs, an internal Ford Foundation committee that sought to assist the Foundation's development of programs and grants related to women.
After she left the Ford Foundation, Chamberlain joined the Russell Sage Foundation as head of the Task Force on Women in Higher Education. She was also the first President of the National Council for Research on Women and a founding member of the Institute for Women's Policy Research (IWPR). The IWPR established the Mariam K. Chamberlain Fellowship to honor her.
Chamberlain earned a Ph.D. in economics from Harvard University.
- New Careers Program -- New Careers Program, 1963-1967 (Box 1)
- New Careers Program -- New Career Fact Sheet, undated (Box 1)
- East Europeans Currently in the US under Management Exchange Programs, 1972 April 19 (Box 1)
- European Doctoral Fellowship Program, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
- Hungary, 1971-1975 (Box 1)
- Poland, 1970-1975 (Box 1)
- Romania, 1971-1974 (Box 1)
- Management Education Activities in Europe as of March 15, 1975, 1975 March 15 (Box 1)
- Task Force on Equal Opportunity and Treatment for Women, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
- Task Force on Equal Opportunity and Treatment for Women -- Background Papers, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
- DAP 73-27 -- Women's Research -- List of Awardees Faculty Fellowships on Women in Society, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
- DAP 73-27 -- Women's Research -- Faculty Fellowships on Women -- Information, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
- DAP 73-27 -- Women's Research -- List of Dissertation and Faculty Awardees, 1973-1974 (Box 1)
- DAP 73-27 -- Women's Research -- Fellowship Information, 1974-1975 (Box 1)
- DAP 73-27 -- Women's Research -- Fellowship Information, 1973-1974 (Box 1)
- DAP 73-27 -- Women's Research -- Mailing List, undated (Box 1)
- MRC Report on Faculty Fellowship Proposal, 1976 (Box 1)
- Faculty Research Fellowship Program on Women in Society, 1974-1975 (Box 1)
- Ford Foundation Faculty Research Fellowship Packets, 1966-1972 (Box 1)
- Alpha -- Women's Programs Information Papers, 1975-1976 (Box 2)
- Alpha -- DAP 749-0816 (WCC), 1976-1979 (Box 2)
- Coordinating Committee on Women's Programs (1/7), 1974-1977 (Box 2)
- Women's Coordinating Committee (2/7), 1974 (Box 2)
- Women's Coordinating Committee -- Policing Women Around the World (3/7), 1975 (Box 2)
- Women's Coordinating Committee -- WCC (4/7), 1975-1976 (Box 2)
- Women's Coordinating Committee -- Women's Coordinating Committee (5/7), 1975 (Box 2)
- Women's Coordinating Committee -- Next WCC (6/7), 1976 (Box 2)
- Women's Coordinating Committee -- Women's Coordinating Committee (7/7), 1973-1977 (Box 2)
- Women's Coordinating Committee, 1976 (Box 2)
- Women's Coordinating Committee, 1977 (Box 2)
- Women's Coordinating Committee -- Foundation Evaluation, 1975-1976 (Box 3)
- Women's Coordinating Committee -- Consultants, 1979 (Box 3)
- Women's Coordinating Committee -- Maren Carden Report, 1975 (Box 3)
- Women's Coordinating Committee -- National Manpower Institute, 1977 (Box 3)
- Survey of Federal Government Grants and Contracts Focusing on Women's Rights and Opportunities 1971-1976, 1977 March (Box 3)
- Women's Coordinating Committee Chron File, 1975-1976 (Box 3)
- Annual Report -- Ford Foundation -- Coordinating Committee on Women's Programs, 1976-1978 (gaps) (Box 3)
- Report -- Financial Support of Women's Programs in the 1970s, 1979 (Box 3)
- Women's Coordinating Committee -- Data Book, 1976-1978 (Box 3)
- Data Book, 1977 (Box 3)
- Women's Coordinating Committee -- Kanter Data Book Correspondence, 1977 (Box 3)
- Rosabeth Moss Kanter -- Mailing List, undated (Box 3)